Now, let's see how to implement a circular queue and see I will show you the code and I want from you
to run it in your own compiler and see and next video I am going to implement this circular queue in
Java IBC, so please write this down.
If you are a C, a lover or if you are a Java, take an example or take an idea how it works.
And later on in the next video, we are going to implement it in using Java compiled.
So include as the i o atch define size equal to five and item size equal to five.
And we have front minus one and three and minus one.
We have seen this and we end and we said that the queue is based on an array and it's called items and
of size.
Five.
We have created an array of size five.
And we have the front end and the rear end next pointing to minus one.
Please go back to the previous video in order to see the animation and learn why we are using the front
and why we are using the the because they are, we need to do pointers and that and that numbers or
the Q items will not be indicating their or their.
The front and rear will indicate the rear order, which is the oldest element that have been inserted.
And what is the newly inserted element?
OK, and this is very important in queue.
So check if the queue is full.
We create a method called is full.
If the front equal equal to rear plus one or the front equal to zero and rear equal size minus one,
then return and one.
Otherwise, it returns zero, so zero will indicate it is not full and one return if it is full, if
that is equal to the front.
So they are pointing to the same index and they are not equal to minus one and the size minus one is
equal to rear and the front equal to zero, it will indicate it is full.
This is the algorithm to check if this form.
Now let's see and the check if the queue is empty, we create a new method called is empty is empty
at the checks.
If the front equal equal minus one, then return one.
OK.
Otherwise, it will return to zero.
It's very simple because we have initialized the front end 30 by minus one.
OK, now adding the elements it is known as in queue, in the queue.
We check if it is full, then print queue is full and we can't make anything if we include an element.
If we add an element that is passed by the argument and parameters, we check if the front equal equal
minus one, then front equal to zero rear equal to a set three or equal to rear plus one modulus size
and then items at the rear index equal to their element passed by the article.
Print f insert that the element brings the value of the inserted animate.
Here, guys, there is a very important metric when ink showing we use modulus size.
This is the trick behind in queuing in a circular queue.
And this and this is a very important trick that that you may ask and may ask in the in the universities
and that interview.
So pay attention for the model of size.
So rear equal rear +1 modulus size.
Here we have to indicate that new rear value now removing that element known as Dec.
So we create a method called in Dec.
It, we start by Int element creating element checking if it is empty.
We can't do anything.
Otherwise it will return to the element equal items at the front, so make element equal to the array
at index front.
And if the front equal equal to rear, then front equal to minus one and rear equal to minus one.
OK, this is how we are adding a queue has only one element, so we reset the queue after the queuing.
Get else front equal to front, plus one more due to size.
You see guys that we have moved and we have used their Model two in the rear when adding an element.
So in any queuing, the rear plus one modulo size is the solution while removing the element front equal
to front plus one modulus size is the solution.
OK.
And returning that element to this is a very important trick that you should concentrate.
Please write them down, guys, because if you are asked in your university and interview, you should
mention that rear equal rear plus one modulus size is that key for interviewing and that front equal
to front plus one module size is the key of the deck.
Displaying the cue, we will create a loop here for an equal two front I that's not equal to rear and
I equal I +1 module size and we are printing items here.
Also, we have used the module size and the codes.
We are using a circular input and circular Q.
And this the the modular with the key of all, like all operation and queuing day queuing and.
Decking and display that's make in that and main and test our coat.
We in.
One, two, three, four and five.
So our cue circular Q would contain one two three four five.
Phase two in cubicles front equal, equal to zero and rear equal, equal to size minus one if we add
new element six.
And our queue contains only five elements and has a size maximum of five elements, and these five elements
are present, so we fail.
And this includes six will indicate that the stack is full.
Now, if we call display, it will display one, two, three, four and five.
If we call back now, we are removing which element it is one.
So if we try to display it, we start by two, three, four and five.
Now in cue, seven seven will replace number one.
So seven, two, three, four and five.
Now we have two as that front and rear as seven.
Display, it will indicate seven, two three four five gay fails to ensure because the rear front equal
to rear plus one, if we are going to include eight, nothing will happen.
It is displaying for us that the queue is full and returns.
This is how we make that circular implementation of the cube of Circular Q implementation in see and
we are going to see it in the jar in Java next video and I want from you to write them down.
Save the logic and understand it and prepare for your.